<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>theory | Stijn Masschelein</title>
    <link>/category/theory/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>theory</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/stijn_profile.jpg</url>
      <title>theory</title>
      <link>/category/theory/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>On nuance</title>
      <link>/post/on-nuance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/on-nuance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Keeping in theme with the swearing, another paper I would like to present is

&lt;a href=&#34;https://kieranhealy.org/files/papers/fuck-nuance.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fuck Nuance&amp;rdquo; by Kieran Healy&lt;/a&gt;, a sociology
professor. He describes the trap of trying to explain complex social science
problems with ever more complex theories. It&amp;rsquo;s akin to the tendency of asking
the seminar question: &amp;ldquo;Have you thought about all these other factors that
also might play a role?&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I see it a lot and when my
undergraduates, honours and Phd students try to improve on a theory. They
just try to add more bells and whistles. I guess in some of the accounting
literature it shows up as tesing for more and more variables that explain
earnings management or that moderate the effect of incentives on performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Healy gives three reasons why too much nuance in a theory is possibe and
should be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If theories can be ever more expanded upon by making them more nuanced it
becomes more difficult to refute them. In that sense, Agency Theory is not
really a theory. You can always come up with a new Agency Theory model that
fits your data. A single Agency Theory model can be seen as a theory and
can be refuted by data. A good theory does not need to be adapted for each
new application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less nuance can be interesting. Healy explains that the interestingness of
a theory is not just an attribute of a theory, it also depends on who is
communicating and who is the audience. In a literature full of nuanced
theories, where every effect depends on country specific institutions, a
simple theory that holds universally is interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also strategic reasons to not care too much about nuanced
theories. Simpeler theories are easier to communicate and understand. They
can spread easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is a different question from &amp;ldquo;Is it possible that your effect is driven by this other explanation?&amp;rdquo;. This is basically saying you need a different theory &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; make your theory more complicated.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
